<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Physical World on Mental Models 101</title>
    <link>http://localhost:42451/tags/physical-world/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Physical World on Mental Models 101</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:42451/tags/physical-world/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Activation energy</title>
      <link>http://localhost:42451/posts/activation-energy/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:42451/posts/activation-energy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever feel like starting something new is the hardest part? Like climbing a steep hill before you even reach the level ground? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone! The mental model of &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Activation energy&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt; can shed light on this common struggle and offer strategies to overcome it. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive in.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-activation-energy&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Activation Energy?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-activation-energy&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, &lt;strong&gt;Activation energy&lt;/strong&gt; is the initial energy hurdle that must be overcome before a process can begin. Think of it as the push you need to get a boulder rolling downhill. Even though the rest of the journey might be easy, that first shove requires significant effort.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Catalysts</title>
      <link>http://localhost:42451/posts/catalysts/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:42451/posts/catalysts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever feel like you&amp;rsquo;re stuck in a rut, waiting for something to happen? Or have you witnessed a seemingly small event set off a chain reaction of incredible change? The mental model of &lt;strong&gt;Catalysts&lt;/strong&gt; can help you understand and even harness these moments. It’s a powerful tool for seeing how progress happens, not just by direct effort, but through elements that accelerate change from the sidelines.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-catalysts&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is &lt;strong&gt;Catalysts&lt;/strong&gt;?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-catalysts&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In its simplest form, a &lt;strong&gt;catalyst&lt;/strong&gt; is something that speeds up a reaction without being consumed in the process. Think of it like this: you want to bake a cake (the reaction). You add flour, eggs, sugar, etc. (the ingredients). But you also need to bake it (the catalyst) to get the final product. The oven speeds up the process of mixing the ingredients and transforming them into a cake, but the oven itself isn&amp;rsquo;t &lt;em&gt;in&lt;/em&gt; the cake.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Inertia</title>
      <link>http://localhost:42451/posts/inertia/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:42451/posts/inertia/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever feel like you&amp;rsquo;re pushing a boulder uphill, even when you&amp;rsquo;re trying to make a simple change? You&amp;rsquo;re likely experiencing the effects of &lt;strong&gt;inertia&lt;/strong&gt;, a powerful mental model that explains why things tend to stay the way they are, and what it takes to get them moving in a new direction. In this post, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the concept of &lt;strong&gt;inertia&lt;/strong&gt;, understand how it works, and learn how to apply it to our daily lives to overcome resistance and achieve our goals.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Leverage</title>
      <link>http://localhost:42451/posts/leverage/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:42451/posts/leverage/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Ever feel like you&amp;rsquo;re spinning your wheels, working hard but not getting the results you deserve? You might be missing a key ingredient: &lt;strong&gt;Leverage&lt;/strong&gt;. This powerful mental model is all about understanding how to use resources – be they time, money, or relationships – to dramatically increase your effectiveness. Think of it as using a crowbar to lift a heavy object – you&amp;rsquo;re exerting less force but achieving a much greater outcome. Let&amp;rsquo;s dive into how you can harness the power of &lt;strong&gt;Leverage&lt;/strong&gt; in your own life.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Relativity</title>
      <link>http://localhost:42451/posts/relativity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:42451/posts/relativity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We often assume our perspective is the &lt;em&gt;right&lt;/em&gt; perspective. But what if the truth is, there&amp;rsquo;s no single &amp;ldquo;right&amp;rdquo; viewpoint? What if everything is&amp;hellip; &lt;strong&gt;relative&lt;/strong&gt;? That&amp;rsquo;s the power of the mental model of &lt;strong&gt;Relativity&lt;/strong&gt;, a concept that can dramatically shift how you see the world and make better decisions.&lt;/p&gt;&#xA;&lt;h3 class=&#34;heading&#34; id=&#34;1-what-is-relativity&#34;&gt;&#xA;  1. What is Relativity?&#xA;  &lt;a class=&#34;anchor&#34; href=&#34;#1-what-is-relativity&#34;&gt;#&lt;/a&gt;&#xA;&lt;/h3&gt;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;In a nutshell, &lt;strong&gt;Relativity&lt;/strong&gt; acknowledges that measurements and observations depend on the relative motion of the observer and what&amp;rsquo;s being observed. There&amp;rsquo;s no privileged, absolute reference frame. Think of it as this: you see a car speeding past you. To the driver of that car, &lt;em&gt;you&amp;rsquo;re&lt;/em&gt; the one who seems to be moving slowly backward. Both are true, &lt;em&gt;relative&lt;/em&gt; to their individual frames of reference.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
